<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>


<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title type="text">Lucas Costa</title>
    <subtitle type="html"></subtitle>
    <updated>2023-08-11T18:38:38-03:00</updated>
    <id>https://Lucascs0304.github.io/</id>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/" />
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom&#43;xml" href="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/atom.xml" />
    <author>
            <name>Lucas</name>
            <uri>https://Lucascs0304.github.io/</uri>
            
                <email>lucas.santos@bse.eu</email>
            </author>
    <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights>
    <generator uri="https://gohugo.io/" version="0.111.3">Hugo</generator>
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Predicting stock prices with earnings calls</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/posts/hello-world/" />
            <id>https://Lucascs0304.github.io/posts/hello-world/</id>
            <updated>2023-08-11T18:30:55-03:00</updated>
            <published>2023-07-06T11:46:59-03:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Lucas</name>
                    <uri>https://io-oi.me/</uri>
                    <email>lucas.santos@bse.eu</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">This study explores the potential correlation between textual data obtained through Natural language processing (NLP) techniques from earnings calls and its impact on enhancing the accuracy of stock price forecasting for the top ten pharmaceutical companies by adopting an event study methodology framework to estimate the cumulative abnormal return in the post-earnings-call 30-day window.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This study explores the potential correlation between textual data obtained through Natural language processing (NLP) techniques from earnings calls and its impact on enhancing the accuracy of stock price forecasting for the top ten pharmaceutical companies by adopting an event study methodology framework to estimate the cumulative abnormal return in the post-earnings-call 30-day window. In simpler words, we created a bunch of text features using modern NLP techniques and tested if their use increase the performance of the task of forecasting stocks returns. In conclusion, this research lends support to a graph representation of earnings call transcripts, as the behavior of the management speakers relative to the analysts during the earnings call is a good predictor of the return of the stocks in a short time frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This master thesis was done in partnership with &lt;a href=&#34;https://djtom98.github.io/#/home&#34;&gt;Davis Thomas&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://vicentelisboa.github.io/about/&#34;&gt;Vicente Lisboa&lt;/a&gt;. The repository with the supporting code is available in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/djtom98/Graph-Based-Analysis-Earnings-Calls&#34;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href=&#34;https://Lucascs0304.github.io/pdfs/thesis.pdf&#34;&gt;complete study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, there has been a growing recognition of the potential correlation between textual data from earnings calls and the accuracy of stock price forecasting, as the textual data encompasses information-rich transcripts of these calls, capturing the insights, perspectives, and market sentiments expressed by company executives. Extracting valuable features from these transcripts and incorporating them into forecasting models can potentially improve their predictive power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this study, nine different models were developed and analyzed to predict Cumulative Abnormal Return (CAR) based on various features. The models were formulated by combining different sets of features, and their performance was evaluated using both ordinary least squares (OLS) and XGBoost algorithms. The XGBoost models consistently outperformed the OLS model in terms of Mean Squared Error (MSE), indicating that they provided better over- all fit to the data. Among the XGBoost models, Model incorporating the graph features and earnings surprise emerged as best performer. The inclusion of graph features, such as the aver- age Euclidean distance between management and analysts, positively influenced the predicted CAR, suggesting the importance of management-analyst communication during earnings calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section provides the methodologies used to estimate the models and generate the features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;event-study-methodology-esm&#34;&gt;Event Study Methodology (ESM)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Event Study Methodology (ESM) is a widely used approach in empirical research that focuses on analyzing the impact of specific events on financial markets. In the case of an earnings call, this methodology can be applied to assess the market’s reaction to the informa- tion disclosed during such calls. The ESM was used to built our target variable (the variable we are trying to forecast), the Cumuluative Abnormal Return (CAR) which represents the abnormal return (return that is not explained by the market) of the stock 40 days after the earnings call happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;topic-modelling-with-dictionary-based-methods&#34;&gt;Topic Modelling with Dictionary based methods&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Latent Dirichlet Allocation (LDA) or other topic modeling techniques which learn topics from the data itself, dictionary-based topic modeling relies on pre-existing knowledge or domain-specific dictionaries to assign documents to predefined topics, thus increasing the interpretability of the model. Treating the corpus as a bag of words, the topic distributions were computed based on predefined dictionaries created by research groups with financial expertise. This lends interpretability to the topic allocations extracted from the text data, and is invaluable in gaining insights into the industry’s financial landscape, thereby aiding decision-making processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://Lucascs0304.github.io/images/thesis/topic_modelling.png&#34; alt=&#34;Topic Modelling&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;cosine-similarity&#34;&gt;Cosine Similarity&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cosine similarity is a metric used to measure the similarity between two vectors projected in a multi-dimensional plane. It assesses the orientation of vectors rather than their magnitude. Cosine similarity finds wide-ranging applications in text documents and machine learning algorithms. Specifically, in the domain of text documents, cosine similarity is employed to gauge the similarity between two documents based on their content. By representing documents as vectors, with each dimension corresponding to a word or term, cosine similarity facilitates efficient text comparison and retrieval&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first cosine similarity features were built with LDA, to capture an embedding space for the earnings calls, by creating a vector of topic distributions for each transcript, and representing earnings calls of each transcript as a vector of values. The best model is chosen by optimizing the coherence score to obtain better semantic descriptors of the corpus. Employing this method- ology enables the algorithm to extract and organize conversations centered around coherent topics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second cosine similarity set of features used TF-IDF vectors, the transcripts are processed and then vectorized into term frequency (TF-IDF) representation using a count vectorizer. This conversion resulted in a sparse matrix containing the weights assigned to each word within each document, which can be seen in Table 2. The parameters of the vectorizer include setting the minimum document frequency to 10, and the maximum document frequency to 300.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;graph-representation&#34;&gt;Graph Representation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The graph representations were created using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stellargraph/stellargraph&#34;&gt;StellarGraph&lt;/a&gt; library, which has support for heterogeneous directional graphs for this use case. Taking the example of an earnings call released by Pfizer in the second quarter of 2009. The major company speakers in this call, Chuck Triano, Jeff Kindler, Frank D’Amelio, Ian Read, Martin Mackay, and Amy Schulman can be observed in a speaker-filtered subgraph in the figure below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://Lucascs0304.github.io/images/thesis/graph_representation.png&#34; alt=&#34;Graph Representation&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-and-features&#34;&gt;Data and Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dataset includes the financial data and earnings transcripts of the following companies: AbbVie (AABV), AstraZeneca (AZN), Bristol-Myers Squibb Co (BMY), Johnson Johnson (JNJ), Eli Lilly And Co (LLY), Merck Co Inc (MRK), Novo Nordisk A/S (NVO), Novartis AG (NVS), Pfizer Inc. (PFE), and Rogers Corp (ROG) from the years 2005 to 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The features were splitted in following groups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Earnings Surprise - Feature that measures the measures the surprise in the EPS, expected Earnings Per Share by the analyst vs the actual reported;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Technical Features - Features built based on technical indexes like moving average and relative strenght index;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Topic Features Directional - Features built based on topic modelling;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cosine Features - Features built using the Cosine similarity methodology exposed before;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Graph Features - Features created based on graph theory like euclidean distance from the management and analysts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the graph features are the one that worked better I&amp;rsquo;m going to enter in more details about it. The figure below shows the embeddings for some companies splitted by groups (analysts and management). The spatial distances between the embeddings can be interpreted as a difference in contextual information contributed to the overall conversation by the speaker. The embeddings which are spaced closer are more likely to address similar topics, and therefore are closer together in the embedding space. According to the figure, the company embeddings for NVS tend to be more dispersed compared to those of PFE, and it’s possible can also observe that several companies seem to cluster together in the embedding space, namely, BMY, MRK and PFE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://Lucascs0304.github.io/images/thesis/embeddings.png&#34; alt=&#34;Embeddings&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results-and-conclusion&#34;&gt;Results and conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tested different set of feature combinations for the prediction task, the best result was given by the model with Earnings Surprise and Graph Features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get a better understanding of our results we used model interpretability algorithms like SHAP values. An interesting observation from the figure, is the avg_euclidean_distance feature, which measures the Euclidean distance between the analyst and management node embeddings. If the distance is low (the management and the analysts talk about related topics or the managers have answered the questions asked by the speakers in sufficient detail so as to influence their respective speaker embeddings), the impact on the predicted Cumulative Abnormal Return (CAR), that is, the abnormal return in the next 30 days after the earnings call, is positive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The managers should designing their speech around the topics that the analysts are interested in will ensure that their speaker embeddings are closer together, according to our model this is related with positive abnormal returns. However it is important to recognize that this does not imply causation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://Lucascs0304.github.io/images/thesis/shap_values.png&#34; alt=&#34;SHAP Values&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the results highlight the importance of incorporating earnings surprise effects and graph features in capturing the patterns. The findings suggest that attempts to measure the alignment of manager and analyst discussions in an earnings call can be a good predictor of the abnormal return of the stock after an earnings call. Understanding the textual data surrounding an earnings call provides investors and market participants with valuable insights for making informed decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/categories/data-science/" term="Data Science" label="Data Science" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/tags/python/" term="Python" label="Python" />
                            
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/tags/machine-learning/" term="Machine Learning" label="Machine Learning" />
                            
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/tags/nlp/" term="NLP" label="NLP" />
                            
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/tags/forecasting/" term="Forecasting" label="Forecasting" />
                            
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/tags/data-visualization/" term="Data Visualization" label="Data Visualization" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Beauty in the Eye of the Voter: Do voters punish female politicians more based on appearances?</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/posts/experimental/" />
            <id>https://Lucascs0304.github.io/posts/experimental/</id>
            <updated>2023-08-11T18:31:03-03:00</updated>
            <published>2023-06-30T16:44:31-03:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Lucas</name>
                    <uri>https://io-oi.me/</uri>
                    <email>lucas.santos@bse.eu</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">This work was done in colaboration with Diane Carpentier and Laura Fras.
Read the complete study.
Introduction Women make up half the world’s population but are far from being equal in positions of power. This study asks a key question of whether women are held to higher standards for any “mistakes” they make while in office and whether this may explain under-representation in positions of power.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This work was done in colaboration with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/diane-carpentier-211248144/&#34;&gt;Diane Carpentier&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/laura-fras-710009177/&#34;&gt;Laura Fras&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href=&#34;https://Lucascs0304.github.io/pdfs/experimental.pdf&#34;&gt;complete study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Women make up half the world’s population but are far from being equal in positions of power. This study asks a key question of whether women are held to higher standards for any “mistakes” they make while in office and whether this may explain under-representation in positions of power. The study describes a highly original experimental design that over the course of three stages aimed to test whether policies proposed by female politicians are equally popular when a man proposes them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;existing-literature&#34;&gt;Existing Literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper aims to uncover the relationship between policy support and gender with a consideration of how the appearance of politicians can impact voter reaction. As part of our analysis we will develop a method of measuring how “likeable” politicians are. Our methodology is heavily influenced by the experiment design of previous studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the experiments that have been discussed use real life politicians and consider their probability of getting elected. This is an incredibly difficult task to undertake as most voters will have pre-existing opinions on these candidates which will influence how they rate their appearance. One of the ways this bias has been accounted for has been by using black and white pictures with plain backgrounds to not distract voters (Lawson et al., 2010; Todorov, Mandisodza, Goren, &amp;amp; Hall, 2005). Moreover, by showing the pictures in a very short space of time (such as in 0.75 of a second) it does not allow respondents to over analyse the pictures presented to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To decrease pre-existing opinions from biassing results, some papers have asked foreign nationals to rate politicians appearances (Lawson et al., 2010). Alternatively, some researchers have asked children whether they think a picture of a politician would be a good ship cap- tain, as most children are not politically active (Antonakis &amp;amp; Dalgas, 2009). While there are lessons to be learnt on how to undertake a facial rating exercise from all of the previous papers they can only take our analysis so far. Nearly all of the papers used real life politicians with a sample of respondents that are all citizens of the same country. Our experiment does not have the benefit of a homogeneous nationality of respondents due to its international outreach which will be discussed in the limitations, however the findings of previous studies still motivates our research and does inform our experiment design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are adding to all of the previous literature by asking a key question of whether the disappointing re-election results seen by women is due to voters holding women to higher standards and whether their appearance matters in such a decision. By analysing whether voters equally judge policy proposals, which is what an incumbent politician should be judged on, we can gather whether voters holding women to higher standards could explain why they do not have equal or better re-election results. Moreover, by analysing the role of appearances, we provide more evidence on voter biases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We designed and runned two surveys in order to test our hypothesis. In total we have 128 observations from both surveys, 22 from the survey we ran in-class and 106 from the final survey after the feedback. The figure 119 shows that our sample is balanced between respondents that were allocated in the picture group and respondents in the picture and text based pathways10. Moreover, our sample had a relatively even gender split of 44% of respondents identifying as women. Furthermore, most of our respondents politically self identify themselves as left leaning, and were mostly 22 and 29 years old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We designed our experiment to answer three questions on the role of the physical aspect and gender in politics. Firstly we wanted to see whether women are more penalised than men for bad policy decisions. Secondly, if physical aspect matters for the voters’ decision making, and if there is a gender differential in how much looks affect politicians.In order to respond to these questions, our experimental design made respondents rate how much they agreed with objectively agreeable and objectively controversial policies presented by a woman or a man politicians with or without a picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://Lucascs0304.github.io/images/experimental/design.png&#34; alt=&#34;Experimental desgin&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We did not find that the gender of a politician influenced how much voters agreed with the policies proposed by politicians. However, by analysing our results using other statistical methods and respondent characteristics we were able to find interesting observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly we did not find statistically significant proof that voters were influenced by the better or worse looking politicians, these results are further solidified by the findings of our linear regressions. We ran a linear regression on average policy agreeableness and average “like- ability” score. In the scatter plot below we can see that there is no clear pattern of policy agreement by likeability and even when we run linear regressions within each policy grouping (e.g. for just the politicians who represented the mental health policy) we see no significant effects. The lack of significant findings could be the result of a limited sample size and a limited number of politicians that ran under each policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://Lucascs0304.github.io/images/experimental/scatter.png&#34; alt=&#34;Results&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, when we analysed the responses to the policies by the gender of the respondents we did find that men were more reactive to politicians’ looks. When presented with good policies men tended to give a lower agreement score to politicians who were looked less “likeable” while for women voters their opinions did not drastically change. We did not see any differences between male and female voters on the role of appearances for male and female politicians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, we did not find statistically significant impact of gender of the politician on policy agreeableness. Additionally, we also did not find that appearances played a role in how likely voters are to agree with policies. We did find that politicians who were classified as looking more “likeable” were more likely to win in a blind voting election, similar to existing literature. Moreover, we found that our experiment design for ranking the “likeability” of politicians was successful in providing information on voter’s opinions. When we looked at the data in more detail, while we did not find statistically significant results there does appear to be evidence that male voters are more responsive to the looks of politicians, especially when they are proposing “bad” policies as are respondents who identify as “right” leaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the experiment was unable to determine whether women are held to higher stan- dards for many “mistakes” they make while in power, the originality of the design could be used to determine whether voters do treat female politicians differently and whether looks matter if a larger more diverse sample was used. We hope that future researchers will be able to build on our experimental design to answer why female politicians are still not treated equally by the electorate even once they have proven themselves in positions of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;full-text&#34;&gt;Full text&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a short version of the study, the full paper is available on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/lucascs0304/experimental/blob/main/Carpentier_Fras_Santos%20(1).pdf&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/categories/economics/" term="Economics" label="Economics" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/tags/python/" term="Python" label="Python" />
                            
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/tags/data-visualization/" term="Data Visualization" label="Data Visualization" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
        <entry>
            <title type="text">Political Virtual Network: analyzing UK Parliament and US congress Twitter behavior</title>
            <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/posts/networks/" />
            <id>https://Lucascs0304.github.io/posts/networks/</id>
            <updated>2023-08-11T18:30:53-03:00</updated>
            <published>2023-04-05T16:44:09-03:00</published>
            <author>
                    <name>Lucas</name>
                    <uri>https://io-oi.me/</uri>
                    <email>lucas.santos@bse.eu</email>
                    </author>
            <rights>[CC BY-NC-SA 4.0](https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/deed.en)</rights><summary type="html">This work was done in partnership with Claudia Abdallah, Renata Canini and Giovanna Chaves
Read the complete study.
Introduction Twitter has become one of the main channels of communication between elected officials and voters. Legislative representatives, in particular, can use the platform to inform taxpayers about their activity in parliament, promote their campaigns, and interact with fellow politicians.</summary>
            
                <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This work was done in partnership with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/claudia-abdallah-403a22148/&#34;&gt;Claudia Abdallah&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/renata-canini-2bb293179/&#34;&gt;Renata Canini&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/giovannachaves/&#34;&gt;Giovanna Chaves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read the &lt;a href=&#34;https://Lucascs0304.github.io/pdfs/networks.pdf&#34;&gt;complete study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter has become one of the main channels of communication between elected officials and voters. Legislative representatives, in particular, can use the platform to inform taxpayers about their activity in parliament, promote their campaigns, and interact with fellow politicians. In this project, we aim to understand virtual networks under different political systems and how they contribute to political discourse. Using Twitter data of politicians in the United Kingdom’s House of Commons and the United States’ House of Representatives, we compare the two network structures and apply community detection algorithms to identify relevant clusters. Our results point to a highly partisan partition of the networks, with the US network’s communities concentrated around the two main parties (Democrat and Republican), and with the UK one presenting a hierarchical structure dominated by the two main parties, but more disperse than the US.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-collection&#34;&gt;Data collection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We constructed our own database from data retrieved using the Twitter API Research Access. During the week of March 27th of 2023, we collected information on the members of the 2019 UK Members of Parliament and the members of the 118th United States House of Representatives using the twarc2 library, which enables command lines via prompt to archive Twitter data in .json files. The first step was to collect the usernames of current members, which we retrieved through Politics Social for the UK and House of Representatives Press Gallery for the US. Then, through the API, we identified which politicians followed each other. Since this process is computationally expensive, we approached this through the smaller side using their following count, as we expected them to follow a smaller number of people than they had followers. Finally, we filtered the list of followings to keep only the aforementioned politicians and, with the help of the NetworkX library, created a dataframe with the structure of a network graph. The twitter data was so collected in 02/04/2023, so the network and results we are going to present are conditioning to the information available on that date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example of the command line used to retrieve the data, where the &lt;code&gt;users_uk.txt&lt;/code&gt; represents the file with the username of the UK Parliament members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
while read line; do twarc2 following --limit 50000 &amp;#34;$line&amp;#34; &amp;#34;following_of_$line.json&amp;#34; &amp;amp;&amp;amp; echo $line; done &amp;lt; users_uk.txt
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;methodology&#34;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the complete work, we implement algorithms to predict missing node attributes and identify relevant clusters. For the former, we use the local smoothing algorithm to interpolate political opinions on Brexit and Trump’s impeachment. Since this is a shorter version, I&amp;rsquo;ll focus on the community detection algorithms such as Infomap and DC-SBM to understand how the nodes’ attributes interact with their predicted community structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We perform a descriptive analysis of our results for two clustering algorithms: DC-SBM and Infomap. Since the results for the first one were less intuitive, considering the structure of the network, we focus on the InfoMap community structure, delving deeper into its interaction with other political characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;dc-sbm&#34;&gt;DC-SBM&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the DC-SBM algorithm, the results are not in line with our findings on the network structure. The suggested partition can be seen in the figure. The US partition reported a Integrated Classification Likelihood (ICL) of −85824.49 and the UK partition reported a ICL of −160382, indicating that the partition found in the US political network is better, since the higher the ICL value, the better the model is at explaining the data. As the results of the DC-SBM indicated several groups that in our intuitive knowledge do not make sense considering the network structure, we chose to not proceed with the interpretation of the results, and move forward by interpreting only our results for the Infomap one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://Lucascs0304.github.io/images/networks/DC-SBM.png&#34; alt=&#34;DC-SBM&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;infomap&#34;&gt;Infomap&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We compute modularity of 0.429 for the US and 0.376 for the UK. This is in line with our previous results for the networks summary statistics section, which identifies stronger links and a more dense network in the case of the US when compared to the UK. Low modularity would mean that a change in one of the components - in this case, nodes - would alter the structure of the communities. This further corroborates our hypothesis that the US’s network is more tightly knit than the one in the UK, which is more disperse. We plot the results of the community detection below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://Lucascs0304.github.io/images/networks/infomap.png&#34; alt=&#34;Infomap&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We find that while the US network is partitioned into two communities, with 208 and 218 nodes respectively, the UK presents 5 partitions, with decreasing sizes. The first UK community has 311 nodes, the second 197, and the third, fourth, and fifth, respectively, have 15, 51 and 7 nodes each. The latter, therefore, might suggest a hierarchical or hierarchical-modular organization, where some communities are much larger than others, potentially indicating a core-periphery structure or other similar organizational patterns. We could think of this structure as either region or party-based: we know that the two biggest parties in the UK are Labour and Conservative, therefore they could be the ones at the top of the hierarchy. The same thing can be said about regions, where the ones closer to London and other major British capitals are the ones concentrating the bigger number of nodes. We verify our hypothesis by plotting the community membership along with region and party, for both networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we aimed to investigate, using network theory tools, what are the main drivers of the interaction between politicians on Twitter. Our main goal was to understand how the virtual activity of elected officials interferes with their political activity, and how it is shaped by partisan and regional ties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complete conclusions are available in the full work, related to the community detection algorithms. We first use the Degree-Corrected Stochastic Block Model algorithm for predicting communities, and find a high sensitivity of the community assignment to different network specifications. This means that many of the predicted clusters are overfitted, and therefore the results indicate several groups that are not in line with the observed network structure. Thus, we use the Infomap algorithm, and find a better prediction of communities according to attributes, which we validate by plotting the community assignment with the expected attributes that define the interactions on Twitter, such as party, region and votes. We find that community assignment is mostly correlated with partisanship, which is stronger in the case of the US, with almost all the Democrats belonging to one community, and all Republicans belonging to another. This is also the case for the predicted and observed votes, but not the case for region, which confirms our hypothesis that politicians from the same party interact more with each other than they do with members of other parties on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
            
            
            
            
            
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/categories/economics/" term="Economics" label="Economics" />
                            
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/tags/python/" term="Python" label="Python" />
                            
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/tags/twitter/" term="Twitter" label="Twitter" />
                            
                        
                            
                            
                            
                                <category scheme="https://Lucascs0304.github.io/tags/networks/" term="Networks" label="Networks" />
                            
                        
                    
                
            
        </entry>
    
</feed>
